Inventory of the Ralph H. Van Deman papers, 1833-1973
Hoover Institution Archives
Ralph H. Van Deman papers
1833-1973
2003C91
Hoover Institution Archives
1 manuscript box, 1 oversized box (0.8 linear feet)
The papers of Ralph Henry Van Deman, a US military intelligence officer, consist of correspondence, special orders, memoranda, personal documents, and photographs relating to American military intelligence activities during World War I and to the establishment of the United States Army's Military Intelligence Division.
Van Deman, Ralph H., 1865-1952
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2003.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Ralph Henry Van Deman was born in 1865 in Delaware, Ohio. He received a bachelor's degree from Harvard University in 1888 and continued on to obtain a law degree. He was commissioned by the US Army as Second Lieutenant of Infantry and later enrolled in medical school at Ohio’s Miami University. His natural aptitude for military intelligence landed him a position at the Military Intelligence Division (MID) in 1897. He is credited with organizing the Philippine Military Intelligence Division in 1901.
In 1907, Van Deman was relocated to Washington D.C. where he became the chief of the map section of MID. When the United States entered World War I in 1917, Van Deman attempted to bring some structure to military intelligence after its merger with the War College, which was the result of a direct order from the chief of staff, General Franklin Bell. His involvement in the revival of MID led to Van Deman taking charge of the reformed division. As the war progressed, Van Deman found himself in France, where in 1919 he served as the Senior American Intelligence officer and the chief of Counterintelligence for the Paris Peace Commission.
Van Deman retired from his military career in 1929 with the rank of Major General. Many years after his retirement, in 1941, Van Deman was appointed as the intelligence advisor to the United States War Department. For this work and his efforts in World War II intelligence he received the Legion of Merit. Van Deman died in 1952. His extensive career earned him the title of the Father of American Military Intelligence.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Ralph Henry Van Deman papers are primarily composed of correspondence, special orders, memoranda, personal documents, and photographs relating to American military intelligence activities during World War I and to the establishment of the United States Army's Military Intelligence Division. The collection is arranged into four series: Biographical File, Correspondence, Office Files, and Printed Matter.
United States. Army--Officers.; United States. Army. American Expeditionary Forces.; United States. War Dept. Military Intelligence Division.; Military intelligence--United States.; Secret service--United States.; World War, 1914-1918--Secret service.
- Biographical File, 1833-1923
  Scope and Contents
  Comprised of materials of a personal nature, including photographs, a graphite on paper sketch of Van Deman, military history of Van Deman, and an 1833 copy of the poem “The Soldiers Return.”
  - Military history of R. H. Van Deman, 1891-1923 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Photographs, circa 1919 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Photographs, circa 1900 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Sketch of Ralph Van Deman, circa 1920 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - "The Soldiers Return,", 1833 (Box-folder 1: 5)
- Correspondence, 1892-1973
  Composed of personal and professional correspondence of Van Deman to and from his family and colleagues. Also includes postcards and telegrams.
  - Letters by others, 1918 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Letters home, 1918-1919
    - June-July, 1918 (Box-folder 1: 7)
    - August-September, 1918 (Box-folder 1: 8)
    - October-December, 1918 (Box-folder 1: 9)
    - January-February, 1919 (Box-folder 1: 10)
    - March-April, 1919 (Box-folder 1: 11)
    - May-August, 1919 (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - Letters sent, 1892 (Box-folder 1: 13)
  - Letters sent, 1918 (Box-folder 1: 14)
  - Adams, Frank P., 1918 (Box-folder 1: 15)
  - Baker, G. W. Barr, 1918 (Box-folder 1: 16)
  - Baker, Newton D., 1927 (Box-folder 1: 17)
  - Brown, Charles M., 1918 (Box-folder 1: 18)
  - Churchill, M., 1918 (Box-folder 1: 19)
  - Davis, Dwight, 1927 (Box-folder 1: 20)
  - Eddy, A. J., 1927 (Box-folder 1: 21)
  - Exton, C. W., 1918 (Box-folder 1: 22)
  - Geary, John W., 1918 (Box-folder 1: 23)
  - General Alby, 1919 (Box-folder 1: 24)
  - General Nolan, 1918 (Box-folder 1: 25)
  - Gunn, D. D., 1918 (Box-folder 1: 26)
  - Hayes, Ralph A., 1918 (Box-folder 1: 27)
  - Johnson, Lyndon B., 1963 (Box-folder 1: 28)
  - Knabenshue, F. G., 1918 (Box-folder 1: 29)
  - Marquette, D. B., 1918 (Box-folder 1: 30)
  - McNamara, Robert S., 1963 (Box-folder 1: 31)
  - Moreno, A., 1918 (Box-folder 1: 32)
  - O'Brian, John Lord, 1918 (Box-folder 1: 33)
  - Pershing, John J., 1918 (Box-folder 1: 34)
  - Postcards, 1918 (Box-folder 1: 35)
  - Ralston, F. W., 1918 (Box-folder 1: 36)
  - Roosevelt, Theodore, 1917 (Box-folder 1: 37)
  - Solbert, O. N., 1918 (Box-folder 1: 38)
  - Stimson, Henry L., 1924 (Box-folder 1: 39)
  - Straus, Logan W., 1927 (Box-folder 1: 40)
  - Sullivan, Peter F., circa 1900 (Box-folder 1: 41)
  - Telegrams, 1918, 1927 (Box-folder 1: 42)
  - Turner, A. Campbell, 1918 (Box-folder 1: 43)
  - Unidentified, 1918 (Box-folder 1: 44)
  - Warburton, Barclay, 1918 (Box-folder 1: 45)
  - Weil, Robert G., 1973 (Box-folder 1: 46)
  - Wesson, Miley B., circa 1920 (Box-folder 1: 47)
  - Whitler, F. L., 1919 (Box-folder 1: 48)
- Office Files, 1892-1918
  Composed of various office documents such as leave of absence documents, memoranda, notes, records, and military special order assignments.
  - Leave of absence, 1892 (Box-folder 1: 49)
  - Memoranda, 1918 (Box-folder 1: 50)
  - Notes, undated (Box-folder 1: 51)
  - Records, 1918 (Box-folder 1: 52)
  - Special orders, 1918 (Box-folder 1: 53)
- Printed Matter, 1918-1962
  Materials in this section include awards, currency, identifications, invitations, programs, and a United States Army War College booklet.
  - Awards, undated (Box-folder 1: 54)
  - Certificates, 1892-1926 (Oversize-box 2: 1)
  - Currency, circa 1918 (Box-folder 1: 55)
  - Double-page spreads, 1929 (Oversize-box 2: 2)
  - Identifications, 1918 (Box-folder 1: 56)
  - Invitations, circa 1920 (Box-folder 1: 57)
  - Programs, 1920, 1962 (Box-folder 1: 58)
  - United States Army War College, 1917 (Box-folder 1: 59)